Everyday as a consumer, you interact with and perform minor miracles
作为消费者，你每天都在与一些小小的奇迹打交道
and yet you probably don't recognize them as such
不过你可能并不这样看
If you think about them at all, you might consider them as nuisances or as obstacles
当你念及它们时，你可能还会觉得它们是种妨碍
But while they're largely unappreciated
不过虽然它们不受待见
these small things actually make our modern lives possible
现代生活却有赖于这些小东西
What am I talking about? Prices
我在说什么？价格
the prices we pay everyday for goods and services
就是我们每天为商品和服务支付的那个“价格”
You might think they're just the unfortunate cost of getting something you want
你可能会觉得价格就是为了获取某物而不幸不得不支付的成本
but they're much more than that
但其实远不止如此
When you learn about the vast amount of information contained within every price
当你明白了价格背后蕴含着海量的信息后
each one becomes a marvel
它们就变成了奇迹
a wonder that helps coordinate the billions of choices of multitudes of people
一个能够将大众数以亿级的不同选择组织进
into a productive and dynamic economy
一个富有生产力的动态经济体的奇迹
Let me explain
让我接着说明一下
Think about, say, ketchup
以番茄酱为例
the primary ingredient in that delicious red source is, of course, tomatoes
它的主要成分当然就是番茄
Now suppose there is a terrible draught in California
现在假设加州发生了严重的干旱
this year's tomato harvest drops substantially
导致今年的番茄产量严重下降
The demand is still there
但人们对番茄酱的需求却没变
people still want ketchup as much as they did before for there hamburgers and fries
大家在吃汉堡薯条时依然想配那么多的番茄酱
but the supply is shriveled
但供应萎缩了
so farmers start to charge higher prices for their tomatoes
所以农民开始以更高的价格出售番茄
that means ketchup makers have to pay more for tomatoes
这意味着番茄酱生产商需要花更多的钱购买番茄
so they charge grocery stores more for their product
所以他们对下游零售商收取更高的价格
and so in turn grocery stores charge higher prices for ketchup to consumers
最终零售商向消费者出售的番茄酱更贵了
The important point here is just how customers responds
这里的要点在于消费者如何回应
A few of them won't care much about the higher price
一小部分消费者不会在意涨价
and they'll continue to buy as many bottles of ketchup as before
他们会购买像往常一样多的番茄酱
but most consumers will care
不过大部分消费者会在意涨价
they will switch to mayonnaise or to mustard
他们会转向蛋黄酱或者芥末酱
or just go without condiments altogether
或者干脆就不用佐料了
and that's actually a good outcome given the draught
考虑到干旱带来的减产，这其实是我们乐见的结果
There simply aren't as many tomatoes to go around as before
因为市面上就没有像以前那么多的番茄在流通
People as a group need to eat fewer tomatoes
所以整个社会需要减少番茄的消费量
and this uptake in the price of ketchup leads some people
而番茄酱价格的上涨正好让那些
those who care the least about the particular condiment to use less of it
对番茄酱最不在意的人少吃一些番茄酱
and that means total consumption of tomatoes shrinks
从而减少了对番茄的总需求
From a bird's eye view
从火星人的角度来看
it might look as though this chain of events is consciously coordinated
这一连串事件似乎是精心组织的
that the farmer, manufacturer, grocery stores, and customers
农民、厂商、零售店、消费者
are all working together according to some plan or to some directive
似乎是在某种计划或指示下共同合作
to adjust to the fact that the draught destroyed a lot of tomatoes
以应对干旱带来的番茄减产
But of course we know there aren't
但当然我们知道并没有这样的计划和指示
There is no bureau of condiments ordering people to hold the ketchup
并没有一个调味料管理局命令人们少吃番茄酱
Information about the need to cut back tomato consumption
人们需要减少番茄酱消费的信息
was communicated organically through prices
是通过价格有机传导的
Or as the great economist Friedrich Hayek put it
或者如伟大的经济学家弗雷德里希·哈耶克所表述的
the ketchup price is, quote, a kind of machinery for registering change, unquote
番茄酱价格是一种“体现变化的机制”
Now multiply this chain of events by trillions
如果把这一串事件乘以万亿
that's the world of economy
那就是全球经济
There are billions of buyers and suppliers adjusting in real time, every hour of every day
数以亿计的买家和卖家每时每刻针对着短缺和富余
to shortages and surpluses
不停地做着实时调整
and they're elaborately coordinating their behavior with each other
他们精巧地协调彼此的行为
and adjust to on the ground developments
并适应眼前的变化
and they don't even realize
他们甚至都没有意识到
they're part of this great global chain of cooperation
他们是这个了不起的全球合作链的一部分
All of this coordination and adjustment is thanks to prices
这一切协调与调整都要归功于价格
all those different bits of information conveyed in that one little number
这个小小的数字传递着所有这些不同的信息
Think about that next time you go to grocery store
下次去杂货店的时候记得想想这事
We understand the power of prices thanks to economists like Friedrich Hayek
我们对价格的理解要归功于哈耶克这样的经济学家
To learn more about Hayek's essential ideas
想了解哈耶克的更多重要思想
and how they help explain our world
以及它们是怎么解释这个世界的
click here
点击这里
翻译 by tcya